RG 033, Works Progress Administration for Connecticut
Connecticut State Library
- Series 28. Architectural Survey, Census of Old Buildings
  - 73. Building survey reports, 1934-1937; 1942-013
    Form reports (FW-6), with attached photographs, containing architectural and historical data on individual houses and other buildings.
    Arranged alphabetically by town, there under by number.
    A duplicate set is available for reference use, Accession T003061. Other sets were deposited with the Antiquarian and Landmarks Society and the Connecticut Historical Society.
    - Andover-Bloomfield (Box 225)
    - Bolton-Chaplin (Box 226)
    - Cheshire-Danbury (Box 227)
    - Darien-East Hartford (Box 228)
    - East Haven-Essex (Box 229)
    - Fairfield-Goshen (Box 230)
    - Granby-Guilford (Box 231)
    - Haddam-Killingworth (Box 232)
    - Lebanon-Manchester (Box 223)
    - Mansfield-Montville (Box 234)
    - Morris-Newtown (Box 235)
    - Norfolk-Old Lyme (Box 236)
    - Old Saybrook-Portland (Box 237)
    - Preston-Saybrook (Box 238)
    - Scotland-Southbury (Box 239)
    - Southington-Stratford (Box 240)
    - Suffield-Voluntown (Box 241)
    - Wallingford-Westbrook (Box 242)
    - Weston-Westport (Box 243)
    - Wethersfield-Windsor (Box 244)
    - Windsor Locks-Woodstock (Box 245)
  - 74. "Keith write-ups", 1935-1937; 2 binders (Box 246)
    Accounts of the buildings of historic and architectural interest in each town. These were drafts of what became, after cutting and editing, the text of the Guide.
    Arranged alphabetically by town, with a table of contents.
  - 75. Guide copy and reference material, 1935-1939 (Box 247)
    Drafts of copy for the Guide or other publications, on buildings, architecture, etc., with related notes, lists and memoranda; correspondence on "Dictionary of American architects".
  - 76. Lists and inventories of building survey reports and photographs, 1935-1937 (Box 248)
    These are mostly shipping lists or control inventories. The first one, "Index to Architectural Survey", appears to be useful complete list of survey reports and photos.
  - 77. Photographs, undated
    Pictures, generally postcard size, of historic buildings and "scenic and marine" subjects.
    - Prints
      - Ansonia-Rocky Hill (Box 249)
      - Roxbury-Woodstock (Box 250)
      - Scenic and marine, by town (Box 251)
    - Negatives
      - Houses, by town (incomplete)
        - Franklin, Haddam-Wethersfield (Box 252)
        - Winchester-Woodstock (Box 253)
        - Scenic and marine, by town (Box 253)
        - Unidentified and miscellaneous (Box 253)
    - Glass plate negatives, T001012
      - Bridgeport (Box 1)
      - Easton (Box 1)
      - Fairfield (Box 2-4)
      - Monroe (Box 4)
      - Newtown (Box 5)
      - Norwalk (Box 6)
      - Redding (Box 6)
      - Ridgefield (Box 7)
      - Stamford (Box 7)
      - Trumbull (Box 7-8)
      - Weston (Box 8)
      - Wilton (Box 8)
- Series 29. Historic American Buildings Survey
  The Survey, whose purpose was "the creation of a permanent graphic record of the existing architectural remains of early dwellers in this country", was first organized as a Federal project under the Civil Works Administration in November 1933. It was continued under the Emergency Relief Administration and the WPA until June 30, 1937, when the Federal project ended, to be succeeded in Connecticut by a state project sponsored by the State Library. It evidently ceased in June 1939, but a continuing United States agency remained, operated by the National Park Service, with the permanent file of drawings and photographs held by the Library of Congress.
  - 78. Building file, 1933-1939
    Reports, data and correspondence concerning individual buildings surveyed. Included are "Progress record of survey" forms, summary cards, mounted photographs, summary histories, etc.
    Arranged numerically according to assigned numbers; a list is in the first box. An incomplete card index by number and by title is in the last box.
    - List, 3-1 - 3-19, 11-24 (Box 254)
    - 25-45 (Box 255)
    - 46-64 (Box 256)
    - 65-84 (Box 257)
    - 85-125 (Box 258)
    - 501-516, card index (Box 259)
  - 79. Building history notes, 1933-1939 (Box 259)
    Summary histories of the buildings surveyed, usually taken from local histories or other published sources.
    Arranged numerically as in the preceding series.
  - 80. "Priority cards", 1933-1939 (Box 260)
    Card list of buildings proposed for survey, often with small attached photograph.
    Arranged roughly by county and there under by town.
  - 81. Control cards, 1933-1939
    Summary cards similar to those in item 78, often with mounted photographs. This series includes also buildings which had not been surveyed and, filed separately at the end, demolished buildings.
    Arranged alphabetically by town.
    - Ansonia-New Canaan (Box 260)
    - New Haven-Woodstock (Box 261)
  - 82. Field note books, 1933-1939 (Box 262)
    Survey books containing penciled detail drawings of building layouts, elevations and construction elements. Includes about sixty buildings.
  - 83. Measured drawings and photographs, 1933-1942
    Completed architectural drawings as filed in the Library of Congress, with related photographs.
    - Photostat of pages from 1941 catalog, annotated with file numbers as in item 78. (Box 263)
    - Photostats (reduced size) of drawings of numbers 24, 64, 68, 70, 72, 76, 81, 82, 83, 84 and 85 (Box 263)
    - Glossy photographs of buildings, Approximately 5 x 8 in. (Box 264)
  - 84. Administrative records, 1933-1937 (Box 265-268)
    Correspondence, bulletins and instructions, progress reports, applications for employment, bills, vouchers, payrolls, time slips, and related papers.
    Unarranged but folders are mostly labeled by subject.
  - 84A. Microfiche of photographs and copies of measured drawings and index to measured drawings
    Microfiche of photographs of historic Connecticut buildings was donated in December 1983 by the Connecticut Society of Architects. Copies of measured drawings were accessioned into the State Archives in 1980 under RG 024. Index to drawings was prepared in 1981 by Jessie Kenny, a volunteer worked from the Hartford Architecture Conservancy. Index is arranged by names of buildings and in a separate alphabet, by town.
    Another copy of the microfiche is classified under: Hist Ref NA 705 .H537 1980.
    Microfilm of measured drawings is classified under: Hist Ref NA 705 .H537 1974.
    A checklist of Historic American Buildings Survey buildings is in
    Historic America: Buildings, Structures, and Sites, Library of Congress, 1983.
    It includes some different buildings from the ones in the microfilm or fiche.
    - Microfiche of photographs and index to measured drawings (Box 268a)
    - 1-40 (Box 268b)
    - 41-63 (Box 268c)
    - 64-102 (Box 268d)
- Series 30. Historical Records Survey
  This project, a country-wide effort directed from Washington by Luther Evans, was one of the major white-collar projects. Its principal objective was to make an inventory of public archives in the States, particularly those at the county, city and town level. Standard techniques and forms were developed, and hundreds of thousands of record series were found and described. Eventually several hundred mimeographed inventories of State, county, town and municipal records were published. In Connecticut the project was supervised by Norbert lacy and resulted in the publication of three volumes of lists of town archives (see item 106, box 317). Unfortunately a large quantity of preliminary, unpublished material (described as "65 cases") appears to have been lost or destroyed by the State Library in the 1950s; it evidently included form inventory sheets of town proceedings and other town records for more than a hundred towns.
  A number of other projects were either subordinate to or closely related to the Historical Records Survey. These included the Survey of Federal Archives in the States (which became a part of HRS in July 1937), the Church Records Survey, the Manuscripts Survey and the American Imprints Inventory. All of these were active in Connecticut. The SFA published inventories of several United States agencies in Connecticut (see item 106, box 319), but the State Library has no working papers or draft material. The Church Records Survey completed inventories of the records of several denominations, of which those for the Lutheran and the Protestant Episcopal Churches were published (item 106, box 316); completed by unpublished inventories and working materials are described below.
  The W.P.A. also supported a large number of other records projects in Connecticut (see item 88). Although these were not usually directed by the HRS, the same field workers often took part, and the work may have been carried on simultaneously with that on the town record survey. Much useful work was completed, such as the indexing of town land records, the installation of filing systems for school departments, the making of card lists and indexes of property records for local taxation purposes, and the indexing of vital records.
  - 85. Manuals and instructions (Box 269)
    Processed copies of technical procedures manuals for the Historical Records Survey (January 1936), the Manuscripts Survey (October 1940), Vital Statistics Indexing (October 1936), Footnotes and Bibliography (September 1940) and other subjects, issued by Washington Headquarters. Also letters of instruction and other directives issued by the Connecticut Director.
  - 86. Articles on the work of the Historical Records Survey, 1936-1941 (Box 269)
    Processed copies of articles or speeches describing or commenting on the work of the Survey, together with the proceedings of a Regional Conference in Chicago, May 1936. Authors of papers include Luther Evans, John C.L. Andreassen, J.M. Scammel, William R. Hogan, Sargent B. Child and Don Lacy.
    Arranged chronologically.
  - 87. Newsletter, 1936 April-September (Box 269)
    Five issues of a mimeographed monthly newsletter for Survey staff.
  - 88. "Index of Public Records Projects", 1935-1940 (Box 269)
    Form sheets identifying each project, with number, location, title, sponsor, supervisor, brief description, date begun and date ended. Some are on forms named "Index of research projects".
    Arranged numerically in a binder with a numerical list.
  - 89. Miscellaneous, 1936-1941 (Box 270)
    - Typed copies of Connecticut statutes pertaining to records of births, marriages and deaths, 2 folders (Box 270)
    - Early miscellaneous documents (Box 270)
    - Preliminary list of organizations which may be available for civilian defense, 1941 December 15 (Box 270)
    - Collection of [printed] materials relative to organizations in the field of public administration, 1940 (Box 270)
    - Outline of "the growth and organization of the various branches of the Federal Government with offices outside Washington" by R. A. McLeod, 1936 June 25 (Box 270)
    - Photographs (Box 334)
      - Old records in basement vault of New Britain town hall (Box 334)
      - Workers in basement vault of New Britain town hall sorting and classifying old records (Box 334)
- Series 31. Church Records Survey
  - 90. Correspondence, 1936-1941
    Correspondence files of Nelson R. Burr, Assistant Director of the Connecticut Historical Records Survey. Dr. Burr was involved with other projects, notably the Manuscripts Inventory, but he was principally concerned with the Church Records Survey, with which most of these papers deal.
    - Luther Evans (in Washington) (Box 271)
    - Norbert B. Lacy (State Director) (Box 271)
    - Field workers (Box 272-273)
    - Others (Box 273)
    - D.A.R. officials (Box 274)
    - Churches (Box 275)
      By denomination.
  - 91. Manuals, instructions and administrative material, 1936-1941 (Box 276)
    Mimeographed manuals, instruction sheets and directives, forms, samples and models, reference materials, newspaper clippings and related correspondence.
  - 92. Materials on Washington, D.C. church records survey, 1936-1937 (Box 277)
    Survey forms, draft inventories, related correspondence, instructions, church history drafts, reference materials and "An introduction to the Diocese of Washington church records inventory" (36 pages typed with bibliography).
    Dr. Burr was Editor, Church Records Survey, before coming to the Connecticut W.P.A.
  - 93. Historical and bibliographical data cards
    Three card files containing notes of source materials, summaries of church histories and descriptions of their records.
    - Denominations (Box 278)
    - Towns (Congregational) (Box 278)
    - Counties (Baptist) (Box 279)
  - 94. Inventories of church records
    Survey forms, notes, correspondence and drafts of final texts of inventories.
    - Baptist
      - Text of final inventory, 1 binder (Box 280)
      - Forms and notes, 6 binders (Box 280)
      - Entries "sent for checking and returned", 1 envelope (Box 280)
    - Congregational
      - Forms and notes, 10 binders (Box 281)
      - Draft of "Introductory history", 1 envelope (Box 282)
    - Lutheran (Box 282)
      - Text of final inventory, 1 binder (Box 282)
        This was published in March 1941; See item 106, box 316.
      - Forms and notes, 1 binder, loose papers (Box 282)
      - Entries "sent for checking and returned", 1 envelope (Box 282)
    - Methodist
      - Draft inventory, typed in binder + handwritten loose papers (Box 283)
      - Introductory history, 1 envelope (Box 283)
      - Forms, 3 binders (Box 283)
      - Forms, 12 envelopes (Box 284)
    - Presbyterian (Box 284)
      - Inventory and forms, 1 binder (Box 284)
      - Inventory, 1 folder (Box 284)
      - Notes, loose papers (Box 284)
    - Universalist and Unitarian (Box 284)
      - Forms and notes, 1 binder (Box 284)
      - Universalist inventory and notes, 1 envelope (Box 284)
    - Protestant Episcopal
      - Inventory, 1 binder (Box 285)
        This was published in September 1940; See item 106, box 316.
      - Forms and notes, 5 binders (Box 285)
    - Jewish and Hebrew
      - Forms, notes and a draft introductory history, 1 binder + 9 envelopes (Box 286)
    - Roman Catholic
      - Inventory, handwritten draft, 1 binder (Box 287)
      - Forms and notes, 5 binders (Box 287)
    - Minor denominations and non-denominational
      - Forms and notes, 6 binders (Box 288)
  - 95. Notes on church records and church history, 1937-1940 (Box 289)
    Reports, notes, memoranda and correspondence, including lists of churches, descriptions of church records and church history material in libraries and historical societies, material on church history in Rhode Island, etc.
    Grouped by subject.
- Series 32. Manuscripts Inventory
  This project in Connecticut consisted of a survey, conducted my mail, to collect information for the planned guide to manuscript depositories and a detailed listing of some of the collections of a few major depositories in Hartford. No lists, calendars or inventories were published.
  - 96. Instructions and administrative correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 290)
  - 97. Reports on depositories, 1938 (Box 290)
    Completed copies of "The Manuscript Depository Form" describing physical facilities, principal holdings and services available, together with related instructions, notes, correspondence and lists.
    Grouped in labeled folders.
  - 98. Inventory forms, 1938
    Completed copies of "The Individual Manuscript Form" describing items in manuscript collections. There are multiple copies of many forms.
    - Watkinson Library, Wadsworth Atheneum
      - Watkinson Library Collection (Box 291-292)
      - George L. Parmelee Genealogy Collection (Box 292-293)
      - Charles Dudley Warner Collection (Box 294-296)
        With draft inventory.
      - Williams Collection (Box 297)
      - Thrall Collection (Box 297)
      - J. Hammond Trumbull Collection (Box 298)
      - Map Collection (Box 299)
      - Miscellaneous small collections (Box 299-300)
    - Morgan Memorial
      - Henry Barnard Collection (Box 301-304)
    - Morgan Memorial, Wadsworth Atheneum
      - Wadsworth Atheneum Collection (Box 304)
      - Wadsworth Collection (Box 304)
      - Wadsworth and Trumbull Collection (Box 304)
      - Trumbull Letters (Box 304)
      - Samuel Colt Collection (Box 305)
      - Miscellaneous small collections (Box 305)
    - Congregational House
      Arranged alphabetically by states.
      - Connecticut-Missouri (Box 306)
      - Nebraska-Ohio (Box 307)
      - Pennsylvania-Wisconsin, miscellaneous (Box 308)
    - Trinity College (Box 308)
- Series 33. Federal Art Project
  This project was the successor, on November 02, 1935, to the former Public Works of Art Project of FERA. Its purpose was to utilize the services of unemployed professional artists for the production of paintings, murals, sculptures and other works of art which could be used to decorate public buildings and for other educational and cultural purposes. A valuable unit of the project was the Index of American Design, which employed artists to copy and thus preserve design elements of earlier American history, such as costumes, ceramics, glass, furniture, tapestries, wall coverings, etc. A 37-page mimeographed "Preliminary checklist of American portraits, 1620-1825, found in Connecticut" is in Box 333.
  - 99. Correspondence, reports and administrative papers, 1935-1942 (Box 309)
    Correspondence, periodic reports on project work, manuals, publicity material and related material. One folder on the Index of American Design.
  - 100. Personal history cards on artists (Box 309)
    Brief biographical notes, presumably intended for public relations use.
    Arranged alphabetically.
  - 101. Card records of artists' work, 1935-1942 (Box 310)
    Large (8 x 11 inch) cards for each artist, listing completed works, with notes of allocation or exhibition.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of artist.
  - 102. Allocations record, 1936-1942 (Box 311-313)
    Form receipts for the loan or deposit of a work, grouped by type and there under chronological. Also a card record by town and there under by institution.
    Somewhat disarranged.
  - 103. Photographs of art works, undated
    - Photographs, undated (Box 314-315, 315A-D)
      Glossy photographs, mostly 8 x 10 inch but some larger and some mounted, of paintings, murals, sculptures and other completed art works. Some but not all have captions or identifications.
    - Glass plate negatives, Murals, undated; T001012 (Box 9)
- Series 34. American Imprints Inventory
  This was a nationwide effort to locate all copies of all items published in the United States prior to 1877. Workers transcribed information for library catalogs, and their slips were later checked and typed, with the ribbon copy going to a central office and a carbon to the file in the custody of the sponsor, the State Library. The central file is now in the custody of Rutgers University. This project became the basis for the National Union Catalog.
  - 104. List of early American imprints in Connecticut libraries (Box Index cabinet, drawers 1-19)
    Author file (somewhat disarranged) of slips containing bibliographical data and a symbol indicating location of each copy (separate slips for copies in different libraries; location code on card at front of file). The main file is followed by draft slips, some that appear to have been typed but not "checked", some that seem not to have been typed, for items in the Sterling Memorial Library and the Law Library at Yale University.
- Series 35. Maps and Charts
  - 105. Maps and charts, 1937-1940; 23 items (Box Oversize)
    Tracings, prints and drawings of maps and charts prepared for various publications
    Item numbers are for reference only and do not appear on the documents. Identification numbers in pencil on some items are noted when present.
    - Ethnic Groups Survey Charts, ink drawings
      - 1. Percentage of each ethnic group working in skilled capacities, Bridgeport. Based upon a 3 percent sample; Percentage of each ethnic group engaged in the professions, Bridgeport. Based upon a 3 percent sample, 1937
      - 2. Percentage of each ethnic group engaged in business, Bridgeport. Based up on a 3 percent sample; Percentage of each ethnic group working in skilled or semi-skilled capacities. Based upon a 3 percent sample, 1937
      - 3. Distribution of Stamford Jews according to nativity, 1938
      - 4. Distribution of Stamford Jews by age, 1938
      - 5. Age group distribution of gainfully employed Stamford Jews, 1938
      - 6. Occupational distribution of gainfully occupied Stamford Jews over 16 years of age, 1938
      - 7. Employment status of gainfully occupie [sic] Stamford Jews over 16 years of age, 1938
      - 8. Connecticut towns surveyed for study of the ethnic groups in Connecticut agriculture, 1939
    - Ethnic Groups Survey Charts, tracings
      - 9. Per cent distribution of foreign white stock by country of origin for the nine geographical divisions of the United States. Based upon figures of the 1930 United States census, 1940
        Number 42 penciled on item.
      - 10. Per cent distribution of population in the individual states of the union according to nativity and race. Based upon figures of the 1930 census of the United States
      - 11. Per cent distribution of population in the individual states of the union according to nativity and race. Based upon figures of the 1930 census of the United States, 1940
        Number 43 penciled on item.
    - Maps, tracings
      - 12. Hartford and vicinity showing area flooded, 1936 March
        Number 24 penciled on item.
      - 13. Map of Hartford, 1938
        Number 25 penciled on item.
      - 14. The Connecticut River, 1940
      - 15. Map of New Britain, 1938
        Number 29 penciled on item.
      - 16. A map of Stamford, 1940
      - 17. Connecticut State map, 1937
        Number 38 penciled on item.
      - 18. Key to Connecticut tours
        Number 39 penciled on item.
      - 19. Location of Connecticut State parks forest and historic sites
        Number 40 penciled on item.
      - 20. Connecticut topography and urban development, 1936
        Number 41 penciled on item.
    - Miscellaneous Items
      - 21. The Farmington Canal circa 1840 showing locks, arches & feeders, printed map mounted on cloth
      - 22. Science explains the Moodus noises, printed map mounted on cloth
      - 23. Waterbury, New Haven County, Connecticut 1936 motor vehicle accidents, photostat of annotated printed map
- Series 36. Publications
  - 106. File copies of W.P.A. publications, 1936-1942
    Mimeographed, photo-offset or other printed copies of publications by the W.P.A. or by sponsors or others using W.P.A. project material. This is by no means a complete file, even for the Connecticut W.P.A.
    - Historical Records Survey inventories of church archives and Guide to Vital Statistics in Church Records (Box 316)
    - Historical Records Survey inventories of town and city archives and Introduction to Town Government (Box 317)
    - American Imprints Inventory manuals and instructions (Box 318)
    - Survey of Federal Archives inventories of Federal archives in Connecticut (Box 319)
    - Agriculture, fisheries (Box 320)
    - Economic and planning surveys (Box 321)
    - Directory of colleges, universities and professional schools (Box 322)
    - Bridgeport adult guidance (Box 322)
    - Fairfield County public forums (Box 323)
    - Recreation study (Box 323)
    - Ground water survey (Box 324-326)
    - Conservation (Box 326)
    - Waste disposal (Box 326)
    - Studies of city facilities (Box 327)
    - Trade and industrial training instructional material (Box 328-329)
    - Housekeeping aide workbook (Box 329)
    - Wages and hours studies (Box 329)